Guide to Philosophy Talk SC1118
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Program audio, 2002-2018
  - Bargaining with the Devil, 2010 Oct 24; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Compromise is the condition of peace and progress. But there are times when we should not compromise when compromise would undermine integrity and amount to cooperating with evil. How do we distinguish between when are we 'bargaining with the devil' and when are we simply trying to be tolerant of alternative lifestyles and political positions? Is it OK to 'bargain with the devil' in the name of peace? When we refuse to compromise on moral grounds, are we imposing our values? Ken and John negotiate the terms with UC Irvine Law Professor and professional mediator Carrie Menkel-Meadow.
  - The Occult Philosophy, 2010 Oct 31; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The occult is routinely dismissed in our times as the province of quacks, the irrational, and the superstitious. But during the Renaissance, many of the best minds in Europe studied the philosophy and science of the occult. The period witnessed an outpouring of systematic philosophical and scientific treatises on the occult. References to the occult pervade the works of Shakespeare and other literary writers of the time. Many scholars believe that The Occult Philosophy and the Occult Sciences, with their search for hidden causes, played a decisive role in the rise of modern science. In this special Halloween week episode, John and Ken delve into Occult Philosophy with Christopher Lehrich from Boston University, author of The Occult Mind: Magic in Theory and Practice.
  - Reading, Narrative, and the Self, 2010 Nov 28; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Reading is a lot of fun, especially narrative fiction everyone loves a good story. But maybe there's more to it than that. Maybe everyone is, or at least tries to be, a good story themselves. Perhaps our very personal identities rest on narratives we form about ourselves, narratives that give our lives meaning, continuity, and coherence. Will the younger generation fashion lives based on the chaos and violence-based levels of computer games, rather than the carefully constructed lives of great fiction? Or is that just one of the old-fogey hosts grumbling? John and Ken swap stories with Joshua Landy, co-director of the Literature and Philosophy Initiative at Stanford University, for a program recorded in front of a live audience at Congregation Beth Shalom in San Francisco.
  - Disagreement, 2010 Dec 5; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Sometimes people who seem to be your epistemic peers that is, people as experienced, as well trained, as thoughtful, and as intelligent as you disagree with you. Should this shake your confidence in your own beliefs? When, how much, and under what conditions? Ken and John search for common ground with Jennifer Lackey from Northwestern University, author of Learning From Words: Testimony as a Source of Knowledge.
  - The Power of Thought, 2010 Dec 12; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Human thought is an amazing thing. It has given us not only science, literature, and morality, but also superstition, slavery, and war. Thought has the power to uncover the deepest mysteries of the universe. Or to create new realities social realities. But what makes human thought so powerful? John and Ken put this question and more to renowned cognitive scientist Steven Pinker, author of the best-selling The Language Instinct: How the Mind Creates Language and The Stuff of Thought: Language as a Window into Human Nature.
  - Philosophy for Children, 2010 Dec 19; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Because of their innocent approach to things, do children make good philosophers? Or do they lack the equipment for clear-thinking? Is exposure to philosophy good for children? Or will it undermine their sense of security? John and Ken welcome Jana Mohr Lone, founder and director of the Northwest Center for Philosophy for Children at the University of Washington. Together they'll put some classic philosophical questions about Mind/Body, Personal Identity, Ethics, and Social Philosophy to a live -- and questioning -- audience of Seattle schoolchildren.
  - The Moral Costs of Free Markets, 2011 Jan 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We live in a market-driven society our day-to-day lives consist of buying and selling goods and services, and to some, our ability to do so without government regulation is the underpinning of democratic freedom itself. Everything has a price, and pretty much everything is for sale, from concert tickets to political influence. But should it be this way? Ken and John explore the moral costs of free markets with Stanford philosopher Debra Satz, author of Why Some Things Should Not Be For Sale: The Moral Limits of Markets.
  - Abortion, 2011 Jan 9; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Nothing stirs up controversy like abortion. To some, it carries the steep moral cost of destroying human life, while to others, it represents an inviolable bastion of women s rights over their own bodies. Despite the polarizing nature of the debate, it covers broad philosophical ground, and touches on religious, political, social and moral considerations. Ken and John seek a dispassionate and rational discussion of abortion with UC Berkeley Journalism professor Cynthia Gorney, author of Articles of Faith: A Frontline History of the Abortion Wars.
  - Derrida and Deconstruction, 2011 Jan 16; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Jacques Derrida was one of the most influential and also one of the most polarizing philosophers of the twentieth century. With his method of "deconstruction," Derrida provided critiques not only of literary trends and philosophical ideas but also political institutions. He won many followers among humanists, but analytical philosophers tended to be skeptical that Deconstructionism was anything more than a fancy name for a mélange of half-understood ideas. John and Ken take on Derrida and his ideas with Joshua Kates from Indiana University, author of Fielding Derrida: Deconstruction in the Fields of Philosophy, History, and Beyond.
  - Procrastination, 2011 Jan 30; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Everyone procrastinates academics are especially prone to it. But why do we procrastinate? Is it lack of will-power? Or is procrastination more like a disease, something that might be cured? Can we structure our priorities in such a way so as to accomplish more even while procrastinating? John and Ken can no longer put off the discussion with Tim Pychyl, Director of the Procrastination Research Group at Carleton University and author of The Procrastinator s Digest: A Concise Guide to Solving the Procrastination Puzzle.
  - The Movie Show 2011, 2011 Feb 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    It's the third annual Philosophy Talk Dionysus Awards show! With the help of listeners and special guests, John and Ken turn a philosophical eye to the past year's cinematic offerings, and present their Dionysus Awards for the most philosophically-rich films of the past year.
  - John Locke, 2011 Feb 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Thomas Jefferson identified John Locke as one of the three greatest men that have ever lived, without any exception.  Many debates in modern political theory have their roots in the writings of John Locke, and Locke s work on other philosophical issues, particularly identity and selfhood, have also influenced generations of philosophers. What was Locke s influence on contemporary political theory and our understanding of the purpose of government? John and Ken are joined by William Uzgalis from Oregon State University, author of Locke s Essay Concerning Human Understanding: A Reader s Guide.
  - Is It All Relative?, 2011 Mar 20; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We've all heard a disenchanted teenager claim that everything is relative and that there is no absolute morality or truth. Of course, there seems to be something wrong with that; isn't the relativity of everything then an absolute? Relativism has appeared throughout philosophy since the ancient Greek Sophists. Proponents of relativism argue that some central element of thought, experience, evaluation, or even reality is somehow relative to something else. Does that mean that we merely obey a code that has no inherent value? John and Ken avoid absolutes with Paul Boghossian from New York University, author of Fear of Knowledge: Against Relativism and Constructivism.
  - What is an Adult?, 2011 Apr 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    In the Middle Ages, people married, had children, went off to war and took on all the traditional trappings of adulthood by their early teens. But today many people put off those trappings until well into their thirties. Some have even suggested that we need a new vocabulary to describe the variety of life stages experienced by 21st century humans. John and Ken explore the new adulthood with Ethan Watters, author of Urban Tribes: A Generation Redefines Friendship, Family, and Commitment, in a program recorded in front a live audience at the Marsh Theater in Berkeley, California.
  - The Extended Mind, 2011 Apr 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    An increasing number of psychologists and philosophers believe that to understand how the mind really works, we must understand it as both embedded in a body and as situated in an environment. According to some, in fact, the body and the environment do not just house the mind, but are an essential part of the mind in the sense that workings of the mind depend upon and exploit the body and the environment. John and Ken probe the extended mind, embodied cognition, and the situated self with renowned cognitive scientist George Lakoff, co-author of Philosophy in the Flesh: The Embodied Mind and Its Challenge to Western Thought. This program was recorded in front a live audience at the Marsh Theater in Berkeley, California.
  - Should Marriage be Abolished?, 2011 May 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    State-sanctioned marriage has long been regarded as one of the bedrocks of a stable society. But in recent times, this venerable institution has become the focus of intense debate, as those long denied the right to marry clamor to be let in and those determined to keep marriage the way it's always been threaten to amend the constitution in defense  of marriage. In the heat of battle, few have stopped to ask whether the state should be in the marriage business in the first place until now. John and Ken welcome Tamara Metz from Reed College, author of Untying the Knot: Marriage, the State and the Case for Their Divorce.
  - Cities, Gentrification, and Inequality, 2011 May 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    In the 1960s, as many American cities burst and burned, the upper and middle classes fled to the suburbs, leaving behind a decaying infrastructure and a socially isolated urban underclass. In more recent times, many urban centers have undergone re-gentrification, and with it the return of the upper classes, safer neighborhoods, and better services. But gentrification often drives poor and working class people from the very places they had called home. Is gentrification on balance a morally and socially good thing or bad thing? Does it serve more to increase inequality or to lessen the isolation of the urban underclass? John and Ken assess the moral cityscape with Stanford sociologist Frederic Stout, co-editor of The City Reader.
  - Summer Reading List 2011, 2011 May 29; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Summer's just around the corner what philosophers, philosophies, or philosophical issues do you want to read up on? Kant's Critique of Pure Reason may not be the obvious choice to take on vacation, but there are lots of readable, beach-friendly classics and non-classics to add philosophical depth to your summer reading. Not to mention new and classic fiction books with a philosophical bent. John and Ken share some of the philosophically-minded titles on their reading list and take suggestions from listeners and special guests.
  - Gay Pride Prejudice, 2011 Jun 5; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The question of gay rights has become a hot button issue, with opposition taking on the air of a moral panic and support taking on the air of a righteous crusade. John and Ken attempt to dispassionately examine the competing scientific, religious, and philosophical visions of the nature of gayness. They explore the consequences of those competing arguments for and against gay rights with cultural and psychological anthropologist Gilbert Herdt, editor of Moral Panics, Sex Panics: Fear and the Fight over Sexual Rights. This program was recorded live at the Marsh Theater in Berkeley.
  - Whodunit: The Language of Responsibility, 2011 Jun 12; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Who is responsible for the broken vase in the foyer? How harshly should criminals be punished for their crimes? Did Justin Timberlake mean to disrobe Janet Jackson during her infamous ˜wardrobe malfunction ? Cognitive scientists have recently discovered some surprising ways in which the language we use influences how we think about responsibility and agency. John and Ken are joined by Stanford psychologist Lera Boroditsky for a probing look at cross cultural variations in the language of responsibility. This program was recorded in front a live audience at the Marsh Theater in Berkeley, California.
  - Atheism and the Well-Lived Life, 2011 Jul 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Atheists don't believe in God does that mean they don't find life meaningful? Are atheists doomed to be grouchy nihilists, finding meaning only in criticizing theists? Or does a world without God offer its own meanings and values to structure a well-lived life? John and Ken search for a meaningful atheism with Louise Antony from UMass Amherst, editor of Philosophers Without Gods: Meditations on Atheism and the Secular Life. This program was recorded in front of a live audience at the Engaging Philosophy conference at Mount Holyoke College in South Hadley, Massachusetts.
  - The Psychology of Evil, 2011 Jul 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    True evil seems easy to recognize: the killing of innocent children; assigning whole populations to death by gassing, or napalm, or aerial bombing. These acts go beyond the criminal, the mean, the bad. But what is the psychology of evil-doers? Are they monsters among us just like the rest of us, with one screw a little loose, or are they radically unlike us? John and Ken probe the evil mind with Simon Baron Cohen from Cambridge University, author of The Science of Evil: On Empathy and the Origins of Cruelty.
  - Philosophy and Everyday Life, 2011 Jul 31; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Philosophy isn't just about cosmic issues. Every day is full of events that raise philosophical questions: why do we eat the things we eat, work the way we work, go to the places we go? What ideas underlie our most basic activities? John and Ken look for depth in the daily grind with Robert Rowland Smith, author of Breakfast With Socrates: An Extraordinary (Philosophical) Journey Through Your Ordinary Day.
  - The State of Public Philosophy, 2011 Aug 7; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    In the 18th and 19th Century, philosophers and intellectuals were immersed in politics and popular culture. Even in the early 20th Century some of the leading academic figures of the time, like Betrand Russell, also wrote for a broader public. Where have the public philosophers and public intellectuals gone? Can philosophers and intellectuals still speak to a broad public? If they speak will the public listen? Or is the public intellectual a thing of the past? John and Ken contemplate the place of the public intellectual in the modern world with Hans Gumbrecht, author of Reading Moods: On Literature's Different Reality. This program was recorded in front of a live audience at the Marsh theatre in San Francisco
  - Time, Space, and Quantum Mechanics, 2011 Aug 14; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Quantum physics is regarded by many as the most powerful predictive theory science has produced. But there is no interpretation of what the theory means that all knowledgeable scientists and philosophers agree on. For example, quantum mechanics delivers no very clear message about the difference between past, present and future. What are the implications for our everyday experience of space and time? John and Ken welcome back Jenann Ismael from the University of Arizona, author of The Situated Self and many essays on the interpretation of quantum mechanics.
  - Deconstructing the College Admissions Rat Race, 2011 Sep 4; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    America's elite colleges and universities spend millions of dollars to generate thousands of applicants, the vast majority of whom they reject. High school students and their parents work hard to gain entry to such institutions, and can be devastated by the rejection. Is there a purpose to this rat race? What values are implicit in the American college admissions process? John and Ken offer admission to Mitchell Stevens from Stanford's School of Education, author of Creating A Class: College Admissions and the Education of Elites, for a program recorded with an audience of high school students in Palo Alto, California.
  - Latin-American Philosophy, 2011 Sep 18; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Latin American Philosophy began centuries before anything of much philosophical consequence happened in North America. Yet in our own time, Latin American Philosophy is undergoing a protracted identity crisis. Is it just transplanted European philosophy? A reaction to analytical philosophy? A reflection of the themes of liberation theology? John and Ken explore Latin America's philosophical traditions with Joesph Orosco from Oregon State University, author of Cesar Chavez and the Common Sense of Nonviolence. This program was recorded live at OSU in Corvallis.
  - Wisdom, 2011 Sep 25; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Philosophy is the love of wisdom or is it? Is this traditional definition outmoded? Is wisdom an anachronism, an elitist concept deployed by old learned people with nothing of practical value to say? Do the professors of philosophy around the world (or on this program) love wisdom any more or less than anyone else? John and Ken wise up with Valerie Tiberius from the University of Minnesota, author of The Reflective Life: Living Wisely With Our Limits.
  - Morality and the Self, 2011 Oct 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Social psychologists have discovered that our self-images play a surprising role in our thinking about everyday moral matters. People who feel they have already proven themselves to be morally good feel less pressure to do the right thing than someone whose moral credentials are still in question. And people often resent, rather than applaud, the morally admirable actions of others if those actions threaten their own sense of moral adequacy. John and Ken explore the surprising ways in which our own self-images influences our moral evaluations and reasoning with Stanford psychologist Benoît Monin. This program was recorded live at the Marsh Theatre in San Francisco.
  - Cooperation and Conflict, 2011 Oct 16; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The Prisoner s Dilemma is a problem studied in game theory that shows how two people might not cooperate even if it is in both their best interests to do so. It highlights the inherent tension between individual interests and a larger society. Should you pick up your trash at the lunch table? Should you push in your chair after getting up? Should you take performance-enhancing drugs? Should you preserve the earth for the next generation? John and Ken find their mutual interests in a discussion of cooperation and conflict with Cristina Bicchieri from the University of Pennsylvania, author of The Grammar of Society: The Nature and Dynamics of Social Norms.
  - Thinking Inside the Box, 2011 Oct 23; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Speaking to the National Association of Broadcasters in May 1961, FCC Chairman Newton Minow famously introduced the characterization of television as a vast wasteland.  And that wasteland has only become vaster though occasionally a flower will bloom, from The Twilight Zone  and Star Trek  to South Park  and Lost.  With help from listeners, critics, and past guests, John and Ken try to tease out the thoughtful from the mindless for a thinking person's guide to TV, past and present.
  - Miracles, 2011 Nov 6; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Religions rely on miracles to demonstrate the authenticity of figures thought to have supernatural powers. Many people feel that key events in their lives were literally miracles. Many even claim to have witnessed miracles. But what counts as a miracle? Is it true, as Hume argued, that it is always more rational to disbelieve the testimony of a miracle than to believe in the miracle itself? John and Ken explore what miracles are, and what would constitute good reasons for believing in them, with Peter Graham from the University of California Riverside.
  - Is Nothing Sacred Anymore?, 2011 Nov 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Tribal societies lived in a world of the sacred and profane, ritual and taboo. Is there anything left of this structure in the modern world? Is anything really taboo, or are things just inadvisable, problematic, unhealthy, unwise, and less than optimal under the circumstances? John and Ken consider what, if anything, is still sacred with Cora Diamond from the University of Virginia. This program was recorded live at Pacific University's 15th annual undergraduate philosophy conference in Forest Grove, Oregon.
  - The Military: What is it Good for?, 2011 Nov 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is the military draft a natural expression of democratic values, or a challenge to our most basic concepts of individual rights and liberties? Are the values that make for an effective military consistent with the values that make for a free and democratic republic? If the government must have the power to defend the nation, does it follow that it must have the power to control events around the entire world? John and Ken enlist themselves in a discussion of the military and its role in public life with Pulitzer Prize winning historian David Kennedy, for a program recorded live at the Marsh theatre in San Francisco.
  - Forgive and Forget, 2011 Dec 11; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    At least forgive OR forget. Get things behind you. All good advice for those who don't want their life dominated by the bad things that have happened to them at the hands of others. This advice has also been applied to aggrieved populations following liberating reforms and revolutions, as in South Africa. But what is forgiveness? What are its limits? Does it make sense to forgive those who attempt genocide, for example? Does forgiveness entail a sacrifice of pride and dignity? John and Ken let bygones be bygones with their guest, Paul Hughes from the University of Michigan-Dearborn.
  - The Examined Year - 2011, 2012 Jan 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    A new year offers an opportunity to reflect on significant moments of the past twelve months. But what ideas and events that took shape over the past year have prompted us to question our assumptions and to think about things in new ways? What significant events – in politics, in science, and in philosophy itself – have called into question our most deeply-held beliefs? Join John, Ken, and their special guests as they celebrate the examined year with a philosophical look back at 2011.
  - Is Democracy a Universal Value?, 2012 Jan 15; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)